ah Jacky está en Colombia para Navidad un año .
um yo fui la día primero un poquito días de Navidad .
and then um I stayed there for a week or like couple days or something like ...
I came like a week before Christmas you know .
uhuh yes .
and so I stayed for like a week and a half .
and when I came back I opened all my presents and stuff .
chévere .
y cómo qué qué te dieron ?
you know .
en Colombia qué te dieron de regalos para Navidad ?
don't remember .
you of course you remember .
you remember of course .
you remember I was there with you ?
oh oh right .
they gave me this really cute shirt .
yeah they gave me a a Barbie car .
it was so fun .
my good childhood memories .
so when cuándo tú cogiste tus braces ?
yo mis braces me lo colocaron hace tres semanas .
cool .
my dentist she said I had to take very good care of them .
and they hurt you know horribly .
oh my gosh I can make like six pages of list that you can't eat .
sometimes no soda no popcorn no gum no tootsie rolls I could go on and on .
it' horrible .
pero te tienes que acostumbrar a eso .
yeah I'm gonna get my top braces on soon during the summer .
oh .
I I I'm sure you'll be fine you know .
so what' your favourite colour ?
my favourite colour is rosado .
it' it' um a very pretty colour .
it would translate to pink .
what about yours ?
mine is red because in the Bible Jesus spoke in red .
that' very cool .
um let' talk about our hobbies .
what are you favourite hobbies ?
I draw .
I sing .
and sometimes I go play golf .
muy chévere .
my hobbies are I .
and swimming .
I I love to play basketball .
I'm in my team in my school .
um I also love to swim .
you know in the pool it' very very fun .
I know .
remember the other day when we cuando nosotros fuimos a la piscina aquí ?
y fue tan chévere .
te acuerdas ?
just said .
tan chévere .
estamos haciendo como vueltas y todo eso en la piscina .
estamos nadando mucho .
mmhm .
también nos nos solíamos un poquito .
we got a great tan .
hablamos mucho de la parque de café Sergio Diana .
y hablamos de las tías .
sí let' talk about our aunts .
well your mom my tía Ana is so nice you know .
yo stutter Ana Howell .
que yo sé .
ella es muy chévere .
she' very muy chévere .
es muy linda .
e mi tía Francesca es muy linda .
tiene dos niños Sergio y David .
.
David tiene cuatro años .
y Sergio tiene diecisiete .
diecisiete .
well .
y yo tengo mi tía Magdalena .
that' my mom .
y ella tiene un dos hijas .
una que se llama Valerie que es cinco años y que está en kindergarten .
y otra que se llama the lovely Chantal que es twelve .
y está en sixth grade .
yes sixth grade .
well um let' talk about our uncles by marriage .
well let' talk about uncle dad your dad .
as you know I call him uncle dad because he' my uncle and he' like my dad .
oh my dad .
so it' like uncle slash dad right ?
sí .
yo lo amo mucho .
I know he' like so cool .
I love him very much .
he' very very cool .
remember yesterday when he took us like shopping ?
that was fun .
de compras .
as he would say in Spanish .
you know these old jeans estaban tan lindos .
I love the jeans .
let' talk about Andrew now .
um he' he' new in our family .
but he' a great person .
yeah um they actually just got married in June .
exactly .
you were there .
you did a great job .
I was there .
thank you .
we came in a limo .
remember ?
that was really fun you know .
that was like O_M_G .
Andrew has a lot of childhood in him .
easter egg hunting ...
oh yeah totally .
that' very very funny .
and rare .
I know .
he is not afraid to sit down with you and laugh .
él es muy chistoso .
y también nació en Honduras which makes him much more funnier because they say a lot of good jokes .
so let' move on to you and me .
you've been here since Thursday last Thursday which was the nineteenth .
yes .
el ...
el diecinueve exactly .
no it was the twentieth .
yeah no it was the nineteenth .
yeah the nineteenth .
and um you actually got there .
and we started decorating for my easter party class .
sí el el día de pascua .
así no para celebrar de Jesus y también del easter bunny .
yeah yo fue tan chévere .
like we had the party and everything .
and we wrote this really funny letter to uncle dad slash dad .
and can I tell them about it ?
sure then why don't we talk about it .
yeah it said happy easter on the front .
and then it said .
dear uncle dad slash dad .
uncle dad slash dad .
we love you .
and we appreciate everything you do for us .
I know .
we do .
this should be your easter present .
we will hang you by your toes if you don't give us more money .
happy easter !
and then we put .
just kidding !
in really tiny letters .
and then in even tinier letters we put .
not !
nope .
and then we put .
love Chacha and Gili .
and then we wrote .
always read the small print .
we also wrote one to my mother right ?
yes .
I'm gonna read it also .
.
sigh .
happy easter .
dear tía slash mommy .
we love you .
you have been very good with both of us .
we love you a lot .
thank you for helping us learn about the path of Jesus .
we love you .
and in this easter season we wish you the best .
P_S for your present it' a certificate for free jokes when you need them .
five dollars per joke L_O_L .
laughs that is so funny you know .
mucha creatividad en nuestras cabezas .
we have a lot of creativity .
do you remember when we went ice skating today ?
oh patinando en el hielo .
that was fun .
that was really fun .
yeah remember after the zamboni came it was like so glossy .
sí .
it was really fun you know .
yo sé .
te acuerdas cuando llegamos a la casa ?
y después mi papi ponió un huevos con plata adentro .
fue cuatro huevos .
tres tenían un dólar .
y solo una de la cuatro tenía diez adentro .
I know .
that was so fun you know hunting for money .
o_m_g I found the ten dollar one .
you found the ten dollar I know .
but it was fun .
I'll split it with you .
don't worry .
it' fine .
um so well it' been really fun these couple days I've been here .
I've been practicing my Spanish a lot .
mucho español con mi tía y Juanjo and you .
yeah .
we've been lately watching home videos of me .
and I was about three or two and a half in one .
and we were watching videos of my Christmas .
and when we were going to places .
and it was awesome you know .
I know .
and one of the videos we saw my cousin Chantal in them .
you know what I ...
yes you know what I've seen from the videos ?
we've been really close since we were little girls .
you know dancing to Shakira .
and it was really fun .
you know in Columbia when you came to visit it was awesome .
before Venesa and Diana were around um things were a lot different .
not much noise .
very peaceful .
you know .
mucha paz en la familia .
laughs .
very peaceful .
but we love them so much .
even if they chipped our tooth .
from a distance laughs .
so Venesa she' like so close to us .
we love her so much .
and we think she' like the best ever .
and you know she' five .
and she' about to graduate kinder .
she' I know she' so big for her age .
es muy grande muy muy grande para su edad .
she' very talkative .
they live in New_Jersey .
yeah in New_Jersey .
said mucha gente que habla español allá .
I know that' like so surprising .
mucha gente .
yo sé .
I mean casi todo el mundo de los países suramericanos se van para New_Jersey or New_York you know .
yeah I know remember when we .
porque there' a lot of chance of jobs .
remember when we went to New_York ?
and like we went in all these awesome stores like the M_and_M store .
it had like four floors .
I know all chocolate .
mucho mucho chocolate .
there' this one floor that you had a total view of Times_Square .
serious .
I know it was fun .
so .
and if you ever go to New_York like you have to go in the giant MacDonalds .
it' like awesome right ?
I know MacDonalds you know .
that MacDonalds is always in the movies .
haven't you noticed ?
yeah I know !
um like the Pink_Panther the inspector I think .
I think it was in this other movie .
he comes to New_York .
and he .
orders a hamburger .
yeah he calls it hamburger .
but you know the exciting thing is he was standing exactly where me and my cousin Chantal .
the people doing this are like .
we're standing .
and it was like awesome !
how do you say hamburger in Spanish ?
I'm just wondering .
hamburguesa .
that' muy chévere .
so why don't we talk about our grandfather .
yeah we have um a grandfather named abuelito Alfredo .
Alfredo .
he is very cool .
yes muy muy chistoso .
he' pretty much the only grandfather we have .
tú te sientas con él ...
tú te sientas con él y te ríes por años y años .
porque él es una persona muy muy chistosa .
very funny you know .
he makes us laugh until we drop .
let' talk about our grandmothers .
let' start with Marge Howell .
Marge well she is very let' start she' a very good cook .
cocina super rico .
yes .
rico sí .
nosotros yo y ella estamos muy mucho tiempo con nosotros en la casa de ella haciendo chévere cosas .
y a mí me a nosotros les gusta hacer como cakes and stuff .
it' awesome .
I know you guys cook a lot you know since she' from the south of Texas .
I know she makes the best cornbread .
she ...
exactly .
she' a really good cook .
yeah so that' the point of view .
she teaches sigh .
yes .
P_O_V .
point of view .
so let' move on to abuelito abuelita Anita .
Anita .
well she is dedicated to God one hundred and ten percent .
she is like dedicated .
no more like one thousand and ten percent .
you know ?
no she is a great person .
and te enseña mucho .
te enseña mucho de Dios mucho mucho de Dios .
y ella le encanta ir a la iglesia las cuatro de la mañana praying like literally praying praying .
four o'clock in the morning .
you know her life is praying praying from three o'clock in the morning until midnight .
she' very very amazing .
now that we talked enough about family let' talk about our homes kind of home states .
I was born here in Florida .
and um um we're gonna ask each other what is our favourite things to do here .
well let me talk about my background first .
well both of my parents are from Columbia .
and I was also born in Columbia .
so my first language was Spanish .
yeah .
español es mi prioridad en mis idiomas .
but you know I've immuned to English more than Spanish .
over the years I had noticed that at first you were like blanked out on the English .
and I'm like ...
I had to talk to you in like total total Spanish .
I know .
but like look at you pro now .
you know .
my background of my stay is I was born here in the city of Pembrooke_Pines .
and I was born at the hospital Memorial_West here in Florida .
and I have two parents of course .
laughs .
and I live in the neighbourhood .
and there' this big neighbourhood named Grand_Palms .
my dad lives in the front .
me and my grandma my mom all live in like the little same community .
and it' like awesome .
my home language is English .
but I've my first word was in Spanish .
it was agua .
I'm guessing that means water .
translation .
duh .
so tell us more about your mom and your dad' backgrounds from where they come from .
my dad comes from the United States from Texas .
um he was born in Tyler Texas .
he only spent a couple years though there though you know .
fue fue muy mucho calor .
he said and you know he said he had a good childhood there .
but he spent most of his years here in Florida and Atlanta and California and a lot of different places you know .
yes .
you know and then my here comes my mom .
she' from like a whole different country like Columbia .
that' where much most of my family comes from you know .
and she was raised on a farm .
and and she loved it there you know .
and she had two sisters .
yes I know .
y mamá también me dijo de de la de la farm .
she ella me she told me it was big .
what did your mom tell you about the farm ?
my mom told me that they didn't have pools you know .
so she'd just take a like a swim in the pond .
in the pond en el lago .
ugh that sounds stinky .
I can't go swim in a pond .
yeah so the rest of my mom' background is now she' remarried to Andrew as we talked about earlier .
and she' here sitting right now live at this interview hearing us so this chat .
listening to us talking about this .
she finds our conversations very interesting .
well ...
she is a very interesting woman .
she' very interesting you know .
ok let' move on to your parents' background .
well it' not very interesting .
but my mom is from Columbia .
mmhm .
she was born on a farm just like your mom because they're both sisters .
and my father was born in Columbia also .
so there' basically no other different country than Columbia .
that' their main country .
that' cool .
y hablamos mucho español .
cool .
en mi casa .
we speak Spanish .
but since I go to school of course I have to speak most of my time in English .
so um let' see .
what else can we talk about ?
so um who is what is your favourite number ?
my favourite number is nueve nine because that was the day I was born .
February ninth .
so that' my favourite number .
it' just very weird .
but that' my favourite number .
mi favorito número .
so what about you ?
tell me about your birthday .
my birthday is on July two five twenty fifth .
and my mom' birthday really weird is four days before on the twenty first of July .
so she had me like like like like four days before .
four days .
after her birthday you know laughs .
wow .
like awesome .
tú fuiste el regalo de ella .
you were her birthday present .
yeah I was her birthday present like four days late birthday present .
that was great .
when uh and my dad I think he is born in ...
born in ...
October twelfth .
twelfth yes .
and um to say a little bit about him um you know ...
he' bald .
laughs .
he' bald !
yeah he' bald .
but you know he still has little hairs sticking up .
you know I saw that picture .
yo vi esa foto de él con pelo largo y mono .
yeah I know .
I know like back .
no no mono .
no it wasn't blond .
yes it was .
no it wasn't !
laughs ok .
it was orange .
ok orange .
en la foto con él con el pelo largo y naranja .
yeah it was like down to his butt .
I'm serious .
wow .
laughs ok .
so when ah were your parents born ?
well my mom was born in Tulúa which is a very small town in Columbia .
and she was born on April sixth .
and my dad was born in Armenia was born in Columbia .
he was born December ninth .
yeah cool .
yes so what about what did you think about that uh rainstorm today ?
cómo cayó la lluvia .
I know that rainstorm totally wiped out .
totally ruined our egg hunt .
you know and then like um you know the movie Ten_thousand_b_c ?
wasn't it awesome ?
pues super chévere .
chévere .
I know you know .
jinx you owe me a soda .
oh ok I'll give you that soda later .
um so ah school .
tell me about school .
your grades your friends your teachers .
we've been doing fractions lately .
and I've actually been doing ok .
I got a pretty good grade on my math test .
and I also had a social studies test .
tell me about your friends .
your friends .
are they nice ?
they're nice ?
yeah .
mmhm yeah .
your teacher what' her name ?
miss White .
is she nice ?
is she is she a good teacher ?
that' the first main priority yes ?
yes .
ok .
what' your favourite plant ?
my favourite plant is a daisy .
just because well the white and the yellow I think are two very beautiful colours combined together .
.
so ...
uh ...
what' your favourite clothing store ?
Love_couture .
mine too .
like the other day I bought these really cute jeans there .
really ?
yeah .
sí ?
también hay una una tienda en Colombia que se llama Azucar which translates to sugar .
it' so cute there .
I love that store .
yeah cool .
it' awesome .
look like you know um what is your favourite thing to do in Columbia ?
oh my favourite thing to do mi favorita cosa de hacer es estar con mi familia .
yo adoro estar con mi familia .
ellos son lo lo they're the best .
that' all I can say .
I also love about Columbia is that it' beautiful climate .
and there' great great there' a lot of fun things to do you know like el parque el café the rivers .
y a veces también Cartagena .
but the best thing about it ...
but the best thing I love to do is hang out with my abuelito Alfredo .
he' like my dad you know .
he raised me since I was a little girl .
and I love him .
I know .
yeah you know um you know he' like the best .
and what do you have to say about Anahí ?
his girlfriend .
la la novia de abuelito Alfredo .
well la primera cosa ella es muy muy linda .
she' super nice .
and she has the cutest dog ever .
it' so fluffy .
she is so pretty .
es muy muy bella ella .
muy bella .
she and she' very she' very pleasant to be around with .
and she Anahí ya con mi abuelito Alfredo de novios .
yeah remember once when you you and me went with my mom para la para un parque .
it was like so cool .
and my mom you and me first went on this cool ride where you like sit down .
and there' this little rope that you hold on to .
and you go .
.
kind of .
but it' not like as high .
and you go around like a circle like twice .
and then I went on .
then you went on it .
and they said that only people thirteen and under could go on on it .
but my mom went on it .
and she was like in her thirties .
and like she went around .
and right when she ended the cord almost broke .
it went .
laughs that was so funny .
that was hilarious .
laughs I know .
it went noise .
laughs .
: that was really funny .
I remember that like it was yesterday .
yeah I know .
it was really funny .
let' keep talking about that restaurant .
.
it' a very outdoor restaurant .
and it has a lot of games like the sky lining game .
yeah .
that was funny .
I think they had to take it down after mom went on there .
laughs .
ok .
so what' your favourite fruit ?
uh since we're talking about fruits my favourite fruit is a strawberry .
mine is a mango .
mango ?
oh that' a I love mango smoothies .
um laughs mango smoothies .
laughs you know what' funny laughs ?
what ?
remember when we were in the car ?
and we were with Francesca talking Spanish .
and your grandma says .
stop screaming !
because you're gonna disconcentrate me .
and I'm gonna think that we're gonna crash .
and all of a sudden she starts screaming louder than us .
I know .
and then we're thinking oh my gosh .
how could she be disconcentrated when she' screaming with us when she' screaming even louder than us ?
well sometimes laughs .
she' very nervous .
she' very funny person .
yeah .
muy muy chistosa .
um during the easter egg hunt at my school the last day before spring break ...
mmhm .
you know um we this kid found an egg with money in it .
and then this he yelled .
money in the bank !
oh my gosh .
kids are really funny in your school really funny in your school .
hablando de tu colegio tu colegio is really big and really outdoors .
and it' very it' very exposed to the outdoors .
I know .
you know the second floor when you're heading to the library and the fifth grade hallway and the administrated office ?
yes .
there' like this pretty balcony that shows like trees and like a lot of pretty stuff you know .
yes it it let' you go outside you know I'm guessing to breathe fresh air .
um your school ...
what' your favourite holiday ?
Christmas of course Christmas Navidad .
pero I prefer Christmas in Colombia .
very exciting .
what about you ?
um I don't know .
easter and Christmas get like all tied up .
I'm not really sure which one is like the best .
because you know Jesus was born on Christmas .
and he died on easter .
yes he did .
he had about thirty five years to live I think .
thirty three .
treinta y tres años .
he started his ministry at thirty and ended at thirty three .
I know .
well we've talked a lot a lot about you know our thoughts and our family .
so ...
um ...
yes ...
so um what' your favourite cartoon ?
gasp you know who I love ?
I love the Rug_Rats .
they are so cute .
son tan lindos .
I like Fairly_Odd_Parents .
magical fairies ?
yes .
I like them too .
they just came out with a new episode .
oh yeah their baby is so cute so round .
yeah round .
so what' who' your favourite author ?
I like Judy Bloom .
I love her books .
yo amo sus libros .
pero me gustaría que ella escribiera más libros en español para yo puedo practicar mi español .
what about you ?
Mark Twain .
tell me about his books .
he made a book about Tom Sawyer .
mmhm .
it' very good .
very good ?
why don't you tell me about the book ?
yeah um you know he it' about this kid who always tricks people into doing stuff for him .
uhuh .
you know yeah .
that' awesome .
well .
but you know his real name is Samuel Clemens ?
Samuel Clemens ?
yeah .
wow .
he got out from Mark Twain because he used to um work as someone who helped like and stuff .
sí ?
and then they shouted out .
Mark Twain !
so he thought that was a very interesting new name .
so he named himself Mark Twain .
wow a very actually very interesting um story .
let me tell you a very funny story about our presidents .
you know in our uh when the Indians used to see pictures of George Washington they would see the pictures of waist up .
I know and like I heard this story before .
they didn't know how tall he was .
so they just added feet .
I know so when they were gonna make the statue he was just this little mini guy muy muy chiquito como una enanito .
he was so little .
it was funny you know .
I learned about that in a book in in my social studies class .
what month were you born ?
February as I uh previously told you .
cool .
February .
yeah .
so um you're visiting here in Florida right now .
so your family' up in New_jersey .
yes they are in New_jersey .
my mom and her husband and my sister are there .
well I love spending time with you guys you know .
me fascina estar contigo y con mi tía with George and uncle dad .
yeah so just like to wrap it all up because we don't have much time left .
um let' see .
what is .
just honestly what is your favourite um ...
let' see .
what is there ?
well why don't we talk about this .
let me put a conversation .
what are your main priorities to accomplish in life ?
goal ?
yes .
your goal for your life .
I'm not sure .
I'm just gonna wait and see what I need to do when I grow up .
right now I'm just getting the grades doing good doing my best and trying hard .
and when I grow up I'll see what attracts to me .
I'm just ...
you know people they do like gymnastics or something .
they stick to it .
I didn't if I don't like it I don't do it .
I'm just waiting to see what I like .
oh very interesting .
how about you ?
well my goals in life are to get involved with international businesses .
I would like to learn about you know businesses in all the countries .
laywer ?
yeah a lawyer too .
but ah but you know international business I can talk Spanish with people .
hablar español or different types of languages .
get to travel around .
I wanna learn how to speak different languages .
I have a lot of goals to accomplish in my life .
I'm just like I said before I'm just gonna wait and see what I like or I want to accomplish because right now I don't wanna make a decision and then try to go after it .
and I don't really want it .
well that' a very very interesting thing of thinking ways .
yeah .
entonces ya para cerrar la conversación qué cómo tú te sientes con tu familia ?
I feel very warm with them .
um I just love it when we can just be together and bond just by ourselves .
and you know I love bonding with my parents because we get a chance to chit chat and talk about what' going on with each other and about stuff that just we get comfortable around .
it looks like you have a lot of confidence .
and .
I had a lot of self confidence .
yes with yourself .